<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ehsan SadrFaridpour - Machine Learning and AI Research</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ehsan SadrFaridpour - Machine Learning and AI Research</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_c95efeb576b66663.png</url>
      <title>Ehsan SadrFaridpour - Machine Learning and AI Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>API Server High Level</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/api-server/intro_to_api_s01_e01/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/api-server/intro_to_api_s01_e01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;designing-a-well-structured-api-concepts--best-practices&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designing a Well-Structured API: Concepts &amp;amp; Best Practices&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📌 &lt;em&gt;Tags: API Design, OpenAPI, Software Architecture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-im-interested-in-this&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why I’m Interested in This&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love automation. There’s something deeply satisfying about writing code that handles small, everyday tasks—whether it’s controlling my smart home, transcribing voice notes into text, or running quick Python scripts to fetch information. However, I don’t always want to be tied to my desk, opening terminals and running commands just to turn on a light or set a reminder. Ideally, I’d like to control these automations right from my couch—maybe via my phone, a voice assistant, or a simple web app. I also want to make these conveniences accessible to my family, who shouldn’t need to know how to code or use SSH.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where API servers shine. Instead of running scripts manually, I can build an API that allows me (and others) to trigger tasks from just about anywhere. Whether it’s turning on the lights, checking my home storage for a movie, or scheduling a reminder, having a central API greatly simplifies everything. It starts small—maybe just a local server at home—but can easily grow with VPN access or even move to the cloud. In this series, I’ll show you how I’m designing and building this type of API step by step, so you can see how straightforward and powerful it can be to integrate automation into your daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-introduction-why-api-design-matters&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🚀 Introduction: Why API Design Matters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APIs are the &lt;strong&gt;backbone of modern applications&lt;/strong&gt;, enabling communication between different systems, devices, and services. Whether it’s for a &lt;strong&gt;smart home&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;web application&lt;/strong&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;mobile app&lt;/strong&gt;, a well-designed API ensures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistency&lt;/strong&gt; – Clear, predictable behavior for developers and users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalability&lt;/strong&gt; – Adapt and expand without breaking existing functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt; – Protect against unauthorized access and malicious attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintainability&lt;/strong&gt; – Simplify debugging and long-term support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-what-this-post-covers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🔹 What This Post Covers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post provides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key principles of API design&lt;/strong&gt; – Focusing on REST best practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using OpenAPI for your API definition&lt;/strong&gt; – How to write and manage &lt;code&gt;openapi.yaml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating API endpoints&lt;/strong&gt; – Turning a schema into working code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;strong&gt;part of a series&lt;/strong&gt; where we’ll build an API &lt;strong&gt;step by step&lt;/strong&gt;, from design to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-key-principles-of-api-design&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🔹 Key Principles of API Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-clarity--consistency&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1️⃣ Clarity &amp;amp; Consistency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good API should be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuitive&lt;/strong&gt; – Easy to understand and use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predictable&lt;/strong&gt; – Clear request/response patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standardized&lt;/strong&gt; – Follows commonly accepted REST conventions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example of a Well-Designed RESTful API:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Action&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Endpoint&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Method&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Get all devices&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;/devices&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Returns a list of available devices.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Get device status&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;/devices/{id}/status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Retrieves the current status of a device.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Turn device on/off&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;/devices/{id}/control&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Sends a command to turn a device ON or OFF.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-why-rest&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2️⃣ Why REST?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this project, I’m focusing on &lt;strong&gt;RESTful APIs&lt;/strong&gt; because they:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are straightforward to document and share using OpenAPI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a clear structure for typical device control tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale well from small, local projects to large, distributed systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-using-openapi-to-define-the-api-structure&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3️⃣ Using OpenAPI to Define the API Structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure the API is &lt;strong&gt;well-documented&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;easy to generate&lt;/strong&gt;, I’ll define it using &lt;strong&gt;OpenAPI 3.0&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why OpenAPI?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automated documentation&lt;/strong&gt; – Tools can generate a &lt;code&gt;/docs&lt;/code&gt; endpoint to explore and test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consistency&lt;/strong&gt; – Forces you to think through endpoints, parameters, and responses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code generation&lt;/strong&gt; – Creates boilerplate for various languages, saving development time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-next-steps&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🔹 Next Steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define our API with OpenAPI (&lt;code&gt;openapi.yaml&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generate the corresponding API endpoints.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement and test each endpoint.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have questions or feedback? Let me know in the comments! 🚀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-downloads--resources&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;📂 Downloads &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for the next post, where I’ll share the &lt;strong&gt;OpenAPI Schema (&lt;code&gt;openapi.yaml&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt; and walk through how to use it to generate your API.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Experience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/experience/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MLSVM Talk</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/event/petsc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/event/petsc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Fast Multilevel Support Vector Machines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/mlsvm_journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/mlsvm_journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computational complexity of solving nonlinear support vector machine (SVM) is prohibitive on large-scale data. In particular, this issue becomes very sensitive when the data represents additional difficulties such as highly imbalanced class sizes. Typically, nonlinear kernels produce significantly higher classification quality compared to linear kernels but introduce extra kernel and model parameters, which makes fitting computationally expensive. We introduce a generalized fast multilevel framework for regular and weighted SVM and discuss several versions of its algorithmic components that lead to a good trade-off between quality and time. Our framework is implemented using PETSc, which allows an easy integration with scientific computing tasks. The experimental results demonstrate significant speedup compared to the state-of-the-art nonlinear SVM libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictive Models for Bariatric Surgery Risks with Imbalanced Medical Datasets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/bariatric_surgery/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/bariatric_surgery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bariatric surgery (BAR) has become a popular treatment for type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) which is among the most critical obesity-related comorbidities. Patients who have bariatric surgery are exposed to complications after surgery. Furthermore, the mid- to long-term complications after bariatric surgery can be deadly and increase the complexity of managing the safety of these operations and healthcare costs. We propose the use of imbalanced classification techniques to tackle the imbalanced bariatric surgery data, including Random Forest, Bagging, and AdaBoost. Moreover, we improve classification performance through feature selection methods like Chi-Squared, Information Gain, and Correlation-based feature selection (CFS).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Multigrid Support Vector Machines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The support vector machine is a flexible optimization-based technique widely used for classification problems. In practice, its training part becomes computationally expensive on large-scale data sets because of such reasons as the complexity and number of iterations in parameter fitting methods, underlying optimization solvers, and nonlinearity of kernels. We introduce a fast multilevel framework for solving support vector machine models that is inspired by the algebraic multigrid. Significant improvement in the running time has been achieved without any loss in the quality. The proposed technique is highly beneficial on imbalanced sets. We demonstrate computational results on publicly available and industrial data sets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ehsan SadrFaridpour</title>
      <link></link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid></guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-me&#34;&gt;About Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, I&amp;rsquo;m a Senior Data Scientist at ModernaTX since 2023. I have a passion for both research and practical implementation, specializing in scalable machine learning solutions that deliver impactful results across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Scientist at Lowe&amp;rsquo;s Home Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;: Enhanced customer experience and optimized operations through data-driven solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Senior Data Scientist at Infor&lt;/strong&gt;: Built predictive models and analytics tools to support enterprise decision-making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Senior Data Scientist at ModernaTX&lt;/strong&gt;: Currently, I develop tools and products on the Data Science Platform team to empower cross-organizational collaboration. I focus on predictive services and chatbots for Supply Chain, Legal, and Human Resources, and automate data connections to generate business insights.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m deeply interested in advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) and predictive services. My goal is to enable others by building and deploying cloud-based tools that reduce process friction and enhance collaboration among data scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ehsan SadrFaridpour</title>
      <link></link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid></guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-me&#34;&gt;About Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am Ehsan Sadrfaridpour, a Senior Data Scientist at ModernaTX since February 2023. I have experience in developing scalable machine learning algorithms for applications in text mining and healthcare. I worked under the supervision of professor &lt;a href=&#34;https://people.cs.clemson.edu/~isafro/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ilya Safro&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Algorithms and Computational Science Lab&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
