<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning | Ehsan SadrFaridpour - Machine Learning and AI Research</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Machine Learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_c95efeb576b66663.png</url>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Fast Multilevel Support Vector Machines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/mlsvm_journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/mlsvm_journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computational complexity of solving nonlinear support vector machine (SVM) is prohibitive on large-scale data. In particular, this issue becomes very sensitive when the data represents additional difficulties such as highly imbalanced class sizes. Typically, nonlinear kernels produce significantly higher classification quality compared to linear kernels but introduce extra kernel and model parameters, which makes fitting computationally expensive. We introduce a generalized fast multilevel framework for regular and weighted SVM and discuss several versions of its algorithmic components that lead to a good trade-off between quality and time. Our framework is implemented using PETSc, which allows an easy integration with scientific computing tasks. The experimental results demonstrate significant speedup compared to the state-of-the-art nonlinear SVM libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predictive Models for Bariatric Surgery Risks with Imbalanced Medical Datasets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/bariatric_surgery/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/journal-article/bariatric_surgery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bariatric surgery (BAR) has become a popular treatment for type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) which is among the most critical obesity-related comorbidities. Patients who have bariatric surgery are exposed to complications after surgery. Furthermore, the mid- to long-term complications after bariatric surgery can be deadly and increase the complexity of managing the safety of these operations and healthcare costs. We propose the use of imbalanced classification techniques to tackle the imbalanced bariatric surgery data, including Random Forest, Bagging, and AdaBoost. Moreover, we improve classification performance through feature selection methods like Chi-Squared, Information Gain, and Correlation-based feature selection (CFS).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Multigrid Support Vector Machines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The support vector machine is a flexible optimization-based technique widely used for classification problems. In practice, its training part becomes computationally expensive on large-scale data sets because of such reasons as the complexity and number of iterations in parameter fitting methods, underlying optimization solvers, and nonlinearity of kernels. We introduce a fast multilevel framework for solving support vector machine models that is inspired by the algebraic multigrid. Significant improvement in the running time has been achieved without any loss in the quality. The proposed technique is highly beneficial on imbalanced sets. We demonstrate computational results on publicly available and industrial data sets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
